<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to the pretended speech, said to be spoken off-hand in the House of Commons by one of the members for B-----l, and afterwards burnt by the common hangman, according to the order of the house ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12187068</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12187068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25613)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 883:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to the pretended speech, said to be spoken off-hand in the House of Commons by one of the members for B-----l, and afterwards burnt by the common hangman, according to the order of the house ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO THE <hi>Pretended Speech,</hi> Said to be ſpoken <hi>Off-Hand</hi> in the HOUSE of COMMONS, By one of the Members for <hi>B—l;</hi> and afterwards burnt by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hangman, according to the Order of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Pretended Speech is faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, Paragraph by Paragraph; the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood of its Reaſoning, and the Malice and Sedition couch'd in it, plainly Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated and Confuted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:55812:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55812:2"/>
            <head>An <hi>ANSWER</hi> to a Pretended <hi>SPEECH</hi> ſaid to be made off hand in the Houſe of Commons by one of the Members for <hi>B—l.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Honourable Houſe of Commons have already anſwered this Speech in a manner ſutable to its Deſign; <hi>viz.</hi> They have committed that to the Flames it ſelf, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to raiſe Flames amongſt others: and it's very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that if this Speech had been Spoke within as it was Printed without Doors, that the Author had undergon the ſame Fate to which he would have condemned the Bill for Naturalizing of Foreign Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, <hi>viz. he had been kick'd out of Doors,</hi> and then perhaps ſhut up in the <hi>Tower.</hi> But ſeeing the Faction do look upon thoſe things as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable, which are many times not anſwered, becauſe indeed unworthy of a Reply, I hope it will not be thought unbecoming any true Engliſhman to make his Reflections upon this Seditious Speech, and teſtify his Concurrence with the Honourable Houſe in their Juſt Cenſures of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This following Speech</hi> (ſays my Author, <hi>Pag.</hi> 11) <hi>being ſpoke Off-hand upon the Debates in the Houſe of Commons, you cannot expect in it the Exactneſs of Roman Eloquence, but you have the Freedom and Bravery of the Old Roman or true Engliſh Spirit, zealous for the Good of their Country, and bold in all its Dangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's but reaſonable to conceive that Ill Deſigns ſhould have a Bad Foundation, and therefore Natural to our Author, who deſign'd a Superſtructure of Falſhood to lay the firſt Stone with a Lie: He would perſwade us that the Speech, as it follows, was ſpoke in the Houſe of Commons, ſo that he might very well take upon him to publiſh it, ſeeing they had the Patience to hear it. What height of Impudence is the Faction arriv'd to! they would not only value themſelves upon the Friendſhip of the particular Member on which this Speech is fix'd, but make the World believe that the Whole Houſe of Commons, who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55812:3"/>are the Repreſentatives of the Nation, concur with thoſe Seditious Reflections which it abounds with throughout; or at leaſt that they would never have taken notice of them, if this Speech had not been printed: So that at once it would inſinuate, that the Parliament is wholly diſſatisfied with His Majeſty's Title and Conduct, and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to ſupport him in that which they themſelves condemn; which being duly conſidered, the Honourable Houſe muſt needs be eſteemed very Moderate in their Cenſure, though at the ſame time they have given a ſufficient demonſtration of their Reſentments againſt ſuch an Injurious Reflection, which might have been prejudicial both to His Majeſty's Affairs and their own Reputation.</p>
            <p>But our Author is more concerned for the Reputation of his own Eloquence, than either for that of the King or Parliament; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore makes an Apology for the one, but none for the other: but ſeeing he publiſh'd a Lie for himſelf, we are ſure that he would never have writ Truth for them, and therefore they are at no loſs by his Silence; which had he alſo obſerv'd, in reſpect of himſelf, it had been a better Medium to preſerve his Reputation than his Extemporary Speech.</p>
            <p>Our Author is reſolv'd to make us a Compenſation for his want of Eloquence, by the <hi>Freedom and Bravery of the Old Roman and true Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Spirit,</hi> if any body can be ſo ſharp-ſighted as to diſcern it in his Off-hand Speech; but we would pray him to reſtrain his Choler, if we tell him that he has entertain'd us with more of the New Romiſts Bravery and the Spirit of the Laudean or Church-Faction, than either with the one or the other of the Former: for I never in my life-time ſaw any thing more exactly copied according to the Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and new Romiſh Maxim, <hi>Columniare audacter,</hi> in hopes that <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid herebit,</hi> than this our Author's Extemporary Harangue, which is ſo far from ſavouring any thing of the Old Roman Spirit, who would not ſo much as ſuffer Lies to be told in Jeſt upon the Stage, leſt they ſhould be imitated in Earneſt elſewhere; that it is every where cramm'd with Lies or Prevarications, as we ſhall have occaſion to touch elſewhere, and at the ſame time to try the truth of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to a Zeal for his Country, and boldneſs in all its Dangers.</p>
            <p>Our Extemporary Orator goes on and tells us, <hi>That if other Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Shires would take the like care as</hi> B—l, <hi>they might be as happy in the Choice of their Repreſentatives; and then, and never till then, may we hope to ſee Poor</hi> England <hi>become Old</hi> England <hi>again, Rich and Happy at Home, Glorious and Renowned Abroad: Towards which this Worthy Patrict has ſet a noble Example; and that it may inſpire and incourage others, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55812:3"/>prempt and enable the Country to diſtinguiſh ſuch from Penſioners and Wretched Betrayers of their Country and Poſterity, is the deſign of making this Publick from a Copy which I procur'd from a Member of the Houſe of Commons, who took it in Short-hand as it was ſpoke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he recommends the choice of <hi>B—l</hi> as as a Pattern for all the Corporations and Shires of the Kingdom. Now there are ſome who will be ſo malicious as to ſay, that by this the Author recommends <hi>J—ites.</hi> which is a plain Commentary upon his former Text, and a true taſte of his <hi>old Roman Spirit;</hi> but the miſchief on't is, that there are many Shires and Corporations of the Nation, where, let the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>take as much care</hi> as they can, they will never be able to make ſuch a Choice except they could revive the Meaſures of the late Reigns, when three Votes carried it from three hundred; and if the Clerks had ſpell'd the Names of the Electors otherwiſe than they did them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it was reckon'd ſufficient to deprive them of their Voice; or if that would not do, they had a never-failing Magazine at the South-Side of <hi>Pauls,</hi> whence they could thunder out Excommunications to ſend Men to Hell, that to be ſure they ſhould not give a Vote upon Earth.</p>
            <p>But if we could get ſuch a Choice as our Author recommends, then <hi>Poer England</hi> would become <hi>Old England</hi> again; <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Old</hi> are miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Epithets, and therefore our Author adds <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Happy</hi> at <hi>Home,</hi> and <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Renewn'd abroad.</hi> What poor Sophiſtry is here to cheat poor <hi>England</hi> out of her Senſes? Does our Author think that the Nation has ſo ſpeedily forgot, that during the laſt two Reigns, the Friends of which he does ſo earneſtly recommend to our Choice, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Riches were ſpent upon the Luſts of her Princes, that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer was ſhut up, and the Orphans Money ſeiz'd; that our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Men were interred at <hi>Tangier,</hi> or buried in the bottom of the Sea, by fighting againſt our Proteſtant Neighbours the Dutch; that we were look'd upon as Effeminate Poltrons abroad, and made Slaves at home by the Violation of our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all the Charters of Corporations; that Proteſtants were made Tools to deſtroy one another, while the Intereſt of <hi>Rome</hi> prevail'd over both; that Standing Armies were levied in time of Peace, and encamp'd on <hi>Hounſlow-Heath</hi> to ſhoot Butterflies, and their Victuals nor Clothes not yet paid for; that our Nobility and Gentry were cut off by Sham-Plots, to make way for the ſtifling of the Plots of the Papiſts; that our Navy rotted in our Havens, while the French King increas'd his Strength at Sea, had Directions from our Monarch how
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55812:4"/>to build Men of War, and was ſupplied with Engliſh Mariners and Stores; that Idolatry was maintain'd by the King on the Throne, our Colleges in the Hands of Papiſts and our Biſhops in the <hi>Tower;</hi> that a Sham Prince was fobb'd upon the Nation to exclude a Proteſtant Succeſſor and maintain Popery; that Catholick Officers commanded our Armies in Chief, and Iriſh Cut-throats were our Life-Guards. Now all this, and ten times more being uncontrovertibly true, let our Author ſhow us, if he can, how <hi>England</hi> was then Happy at home and Glorious and Renown'd abroad: and though it's true that <hi>England</hi> was Richer then than at preſent; yet thoſe were the Cauſes that ſhe is now become Poorer, and brought on the War which does ſo much Exhauſt her.</p>
            <p>But to make our Author ſenſible that we can do more than Recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, let him be pleas'd to tell us, if ever <hi>England</hi> was bleſs'd before with a Proteſtant King and Queen, or free of ſuſpicion from Q. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>'s time till now, that Popery was favoured by the Court? When was it that ever <hi>England</hi>'s Monarch was Generaliſſimo of <hi>Europe,</hi> and not only Arbitrator of her Differences, but in a manner her Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver? We us'd to value our ſelves mightily that we could turn the ballance, and is it nothing now that we are the Champions of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> and our King the Head of the Greateſt League that ever was made in the Weſtern World? Was <hi>England</hi>'s Banner ever ſo much reverenc'd abroad, and not only her Terrour, but her Armies ſpread beyond the <hi>Aples?</hi> Was it ever known till now, that the Emperour, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Electors of the Empire, would ſubmit to the Arms and Conduct of an Engliſh King, and command their Generals to obey his Orders? Was there ever ſuch a Congreſs of Princes and Ambaſſadors in <hi>Europe,</hi> as aſſembled to Conſult His Majeſty at the <hi>Hague?</hi> Was ever the Roaring of our Engliſh Lions heard with ſo much Majeſty, not only in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> but in the Bowels of <hi>Italy?</hi> Was there ever a more Glorious Victory obtain'd at Sea than that over the French under King <hi>William</hi>'s Banner, which laid <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV th's Glory in the bottom of the Depths? Had we ever a King of <hi>England</hi> who ſignaliz'd himſelf perſonally in ſo many Battels, though there be more Danger in one now than there was in twenty in former Ages? Or had we ever any who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook ſo many perillous Voyages by Sea, for the Honour of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as he has done? Had we ever a Prince who did ſo gloriouſly reſcue our own Religion and Liberty, and not only ours, but thoſe of <hi>Europe,</hi> and who is not meerly a Nominal but real Defender of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55812:4"/>Faith? does not ſend counterfeit Aſſiſtance to Foreign Proteſtants as K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. did to thoſe of <hi>Rochel,</hi> and at the ſame time ruin them by his Men of War, but hath actually reſtored the Antient Church of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> who under his auſpicious Protection have regained their Country, and reeſtabliſhed their deſolate Churches. Had we ever a Prince before, who made it his Buſineſs to hinder one Party of our Britiſh Proteſtants to deſtroy the other, and evidences a truly paternal Care over all his Subjects? Had we ever a Prince who by an unparallel'd Clemency to his Enemies, was almoſt cruel to himſelf and his Friends? Or had we ever a King before who could command both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> two of the moſt formidable Powers in <hi>Europe?</hi> Or could boaſt of an Univerſal Kindred or Alliance with almoſt all the Sovereign Princes in Chriſtendom? So that for the Point of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he hath made <hi>England</hi> higher than ever; and that ſhe is not Richer is none of his Fault, but juſtly chargeable on thoſe of our Author's Principles, who betray his Counſels, obſtruct his Meaſures, prevent his having the united Service of his Proteſtant Subjects, and ſtudy more, under a Notion of humouring the Church Faction, to ruin the Church her ſelf, by keeping up of Diviſions amongſt Proteſtants, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Liberty of <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> than either to promote their Countries Good, or their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign's Honour, by a Cordial Oppoſition to the French King, who is the Common Enemy of Chriſtendom himſelf, and in League with thoſe who have always owned themſelves to be ſuch. And this I hope is ſufficient to demonſtrate whether the Choice of <hi>B—l</hi> ought to be a Pattern to the Nation, and to enable the Country to diſtinguiſh betwixt ſuch as are really Penſioners to the French King and thoſe who are falſly eſteemed ſuch to King <hi>William,</hi> becauſe perhaps his Servants or Officers, and willing rather to grant him their early Aſſiſtance againſt the Common Enemy, than tenaciouſly to contradict him in ſuch things as ſome of our Author's Kidney have labour'd to perſwade him, are his incommunicable Prerogative which he ought not to part with, on purpoſe to make a Rupture betwixt him and his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that ſo they may take advantage from our mutual Confuſions, and like this venomous Libeller endeavour to procure Tumults, and betray their Country and Poſterity to Popery and Slavery.</p>
            <p>But now, Gentlemen, <hi>Si vobis placet audire fabulam,</hi> here's one for you with a couple of Lies in it's Belly ſpick and ſpan new from the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobite Mint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Speaker,</hi> (ſays my Author) <hi>I have heard of a Ship in a violent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55812:5"/>Strom in danger of periſhing every Momem;</hi> [<hi>It was not ſuch a ſham Sterm we were lately entertain'd with in the</hi> Gazette <hi>which deceives the People, that many Ships going for</hi> France <hi>laden with Corn and ſeveral ſorts of Proviſions for the uſe of our Dutch Allies, to enable them to live Cheap by making the ſame Dear at Home; perhaps ſome was for the ſuppert of our half ſtarv'd and unpaid Engliſh Souldiers now in</hi> Flanders, <hi>when periſh'd likewiſe more than</hi> 700 <hi>Sailors, who have left thouſands of Widows, Children and poor Relations to curſe our Conduct at Sea; the Cauſe of this Calamity in ſuch a dreadful Storm it was that the foreſaid Ship was in</hi>]; <hi>when the good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander ſeeing the Danger and apprehending Death, deſir'd his Crew to aſſiſt with Reſolution, and preſerve themſelves and the Ship; which the Sailors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to do, be retired to his Cabin, humbled himſelf in Prayer, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored the Powers that alone can ſave in time of Need, that though the Ship and the Company might be juſtly ſwallowed up for the Diſobedience of the Sailors, yet that he and his Cabin might ſuffer no Damage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were an eaſy Matter to turn over <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s or <hi>Phedrus</hi> his Fables, and repay our Author in his own Com, but I ſhall content my ſelf with an Animadverſion on his Moral, and take his Lies to Task which are more material. To begin with his Lies, they are foiſted into the middle of his Fable with a very huge and bulky Parentheſis; but our Author was full of them, and out they muſt tumble: Well, that you may be ſure he himſelf is a Man of Truth, he begins and charges the <hi>Gazette</hi> with a Lie; and that which is worſe, that it deceives the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But by our Author's leave, If the Loſs of the Ships bound to <hi>France</hi> with Corn was a Lie, it was made by their own Friends the <hi>Danes;</hi> and though perhaps the Number might not be ſo great as at firſt given out, yet the main of the Story does certainly hold; nor do I believe that our Author has better Correſpondence than that which comes to our Secretary of State, and is publiſhed twice <hi>per</hi> Week in the <hi>Gazette</hi> by Authority: but the Miſchief on't is, ſay the <hi>Jucobites,</hi> That they agree with the Gazetteer to cheat the People: whether or not our Author underſtands French or Dutch, it's not material; but if he had conſulted any of his Friends that do, they could have told him that all the <hi>Gazettes</hi> which come from beyond Sea, that of <hi>Paris</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, had the ſame Relation; and there are private Letters ſtill to be ſeen in Town of the ſame Tenor, and that's more than I am ſure he can produce, except they be of his own and his Friends forging for his ſeventy Ships loſt on the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> which no Body but he and they ever heard of: but it's no matter to him whether the Story be true or falſe, it ſerves his turn to make the Government odious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55812:5"/>to the People, as if they had a Deſign to ſtarve their own Subjects while they feed and pamper our Allies the Dutch; and leſt his own Prayers ſhould not be ſucceſsful, they are back'd with the Curſes of thouſands of Widwos, Children and Relations of 700 drown'd Sailors, who curſe our Conduct at Sea, the Cauſe of this Calamity, though before he had told us that it was <hi>cauſed by a Storm,</hi> and that I ſuppoſe may happen where there's the beſt of Conduct; but right or wrong, our Conduct muſt be blam'd, elſe the thouſands of Widows left by the 700 Sailors can't tell whither to direct their Curſes; and that they may do it the more heartily, they muſt be told that the Corn was deſign'd for the Dutch, to make them lives Cheap while we pine for Want: And to give their Curſes ſtill the ſharper Edg, our Author would inſinuate that the Stars in their Courſes fight againſt King <hi>William,</hi> whilſt <hi>Claudian</hi>'s Verſes are applicable to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. <hi>O nimium dilecte Dee, cui militat Aether, &amp; conjurati veniunt ad Claſſica Vents.</hi> But it's an eaſy matter for one who can print ſuch Speeches Without, as were never made within Doors, to invent Lies and contradict Truths, <hi>ſimiles habent ſua Labra Lactucas,</hi> Such Cauſes require ſuch Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. The <hi>Paris</hi> Gazetteer is known to be a Liar all over <hi>Europe,</hi> and we can point at a Reign or two when the Engliſh Gazetteer labour'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Infamy; ſo that it's no wonder that the Faction, who never were Clients of Truth themſelves, ſhould expect nothing but Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods from others: but bleſſed be God the preſent Government neither needs nor does make uſe of ſuch Methods to ſupport it; and though his falſe Story of ſeventy of our Ships Joaden with Corn, and 700 of our Sailors being drown'd, may be a Cordial to keep up the droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirits of the Jacobites for a while, they will find their Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to be a Cheat at laſt.</p>
            <p>But now for his Moral, he goes on thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I cannot as that good Commander did, be ſo vain as to hope that either my ſelf, or the Place for which I ſerve can be preſerved from the general Inundation which this Bill we are now debating lets in one the Liberties of my native Country and Country-men, and therefore be unconcerned for the Good of</hi> England, <hi>provided</hi> B—l <hi>were Safe. To hope for and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Happineſs in Life, when all Mankind but my ſelf are Dead, would not be more deceiving, than to propoſe Comfort and Security to my ſelf and Corporation, when Strangers are admitted to poſſeſs, and enjoy by a Law, all that's Valuable in this Kingdom; For this Bill doth enfranchiſe all Strangers, that will Swear and Proteſt againſt Popery, with the Liberty of every Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, after the vaſt Expence of Treaſure and Engliſh Blood is hath coſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55812:6"/>this Kingdom in all Times and Ages of our Forefathers, to ſecure them to themſelves and their Poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's a very ſevere Libel againſt the Repreſentatives of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that none of them have any Concern for the Publick Good but himſelf; not one Soul more who will help to keep up the Banks againſt a Deluge of Foreigners which is ready to overflow us; for it ſeems by him that all the reſt are like the perverſe Sailors who deſerve to be ſwallowed up for their Diſobedience, and Sir <hi>J. K</hi>— and his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration only to be ſafe. But not ſo faſt, Can any Man of common Senſe think that ſo many Gentlemen, who have ventured their Lives, Eſtates, and all that is dear to them for the Defence of their Engliſh Liberties, ſhould be all of a ſudden ſo enamoured on Foreigners, as to ſuffer them tamely to ſwallow up all without oppoſition, if there were any ſuch Hazard, or that Sir <hi>J. K—</hi> ſhould alone ſee the Danger, and all the reſt be as blind as Beetles? This ſeems every whit as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable in our Author, as that which he himſelf ridicules in the next Paragraph but one, That we ſhould reckon our ſelves Wiſer than our Forefathers; for here he prefers Sir <hi>J.K</hi>'s Sight and Senſe to that of the whole Houſe of Commons, who are his Contemporaries, and in all Circumſtances not only Equal but Superiour to him or any one ſingle Perſon in Foreſight and Judgment: whereas the Abſurdity is not ſo great, if as to the changing of mutable Conſtitutions, we pretend to be as good Judges as our Forefathers, ſeeing we ſtand upon their Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and muſt in the Senſe of all Mankind know our own Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances better than they could do, except they had been all of them inſpir'd with a Spirit of Prophecy. But that which ſticks in our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Stomach is, that all Strangers that will Swear and Proteſt againſt Popery, ſhould be admitted to poſſeſs, by a Law, all that's valuable in this Kingdom, with the liberty of every Engliſh-man. He would do well to explain himſelf, whether it be this Teſt or not that vexes him; perhaps he is angry that they ſhould be oblig'd to abjure Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, which is contrary indeed to his <hi>Roman Spirit,</hi> and according to the Charity of the Laudean or Church Faction, it would have been a much more acceptable Teſt to have made them abjure Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and ſo unchurch all thoſe of the Reformed Communion Abroad for want of Epiſcopal Ordination, according to the new Method of Charity to the French Proteſtant Divines, to deny them a Benefice without they ſubmit to a Reordination, and cut off a Third or a Fourth of the Peoples Bounty from thoſe who do not Conform, though they were obliged to ſwear in the Confeſſion of their own Church,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55812:6"/>that they believe no Eccleſiaſtical Order of Divine Right ſuperior to that of a Presbyter. But further, what if the promoters of that Bill do find it requiſite to have an Alloy of Foreign Proteſtants, who will be true to the Intereſt of their Religion, and conſequently of the Country where it is maintain'd, and not ſo inconſiſtent with either as a certain ſort of Men amongſt us, who will needs be call'd Proteſtants and Engliſhmen, and yet promote the Intereſt of the late King, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV, to the utter overthrow of our Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? and ſeeing thoſe Foreigners were Inſtruments under God and our Gracious Soveraign, to reſcue that Religion, and thoſe Liberties which have coſt ſo much Engliſh Blood and Treaſure, when both of them were ſo baſely betrayed by thoſe who <hi>(ſi diis placet)</hi> will needs be called Engliſh-men and Proteſtants; I ſay, why may not thoſe Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers who were the Inſtruments to reſcue them, be uſeful Inſtruments likewiſe to preſerve them, eſpecially when they are no more Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but Engliſhmen by Naturalization, and ſo will be obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our Rights and Liberties as their own?</p>
            <p>But to return to our Extemporary Orator, he goes on thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore, Mr. Speaker, I muſt beg Pardon if at this time I cannot be ſilent, but expreſs a zealous Concern, as well for the Kingdom in General, as for the Place I repreſent in Particular: And I am more moved thereunto, whilſt I ſee ſo many Members ſent here by their Country for the Conſervation of the Engliſhmens Liberties, ſo warm as to part with all to Strangers with one Vote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I durſt venture an even Wager, that this Gentleman will be very angry at any Man who defends Extemporary Prayers to God, and yet he thinks himſelf extreamly well qualify'd for Extemporary Speeches to Men; His General and Particular Zeal do ſo fill his Heart, that it looſes the Strings of his Tongue, this being indeed ſuch an occaſion as would have made <hi>Craeſus's</hi> dumb Son to ſpeak, to ſee thoſe who are intruſted with the Conſervation of our Liberties to part with <hi>all</hi> to Strangers: Whereas I believe that the Bill intended them only a <hi>ſhare,</hi> and this Gentleman finding the Houſe grow warm upon the Matter, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to expel one Heat by another; and it ſeems the Commons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of his Method, for they have dealt pretty warmly with his Speech, which I hope hath in ſome meaſure driven out his unnatural Heat.</p>
            <p>His general Zeal made him diſcharge furiouſly againſt the Bill; and now his particular Zeal falls on the Arguments made uſe of to defend it.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:55812:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Argument of the Honorable Perſon near me</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to render all the Care of our Forefathers of no Eſteem amongst us, who are or ought to be the Repreſentatives of the Kingdom, was to prove, that this Age and Generation are wiſer</hi> (he did not ſay Honeſter) <hi>than the former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I remember</hi> (continues he) <hi>that a Weſt-country Man, many Years paſt, undertook to prove the ſame to me and my Company beyond-Sea, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring his Father was a Fool to him: I yielded him that Point, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding both to be ſuch; and yet our Fore-fathers might be wiſe. Men. I ſhall not at this time queſtion the Wiſdom of thoſe who promote the Bill, or their Fathers: For my ſelf I declare in behalf of the Wiſdom and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty of our Predeceſſers, nor can I aſſent to the yielding up of the Liberties and Laws they derived unto us, only becauſe ſome Gentlemen think better of themſelves, and perhaps miſtakenly, than of their Parents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Burden of all this Crambo is, that Sir <hi>J.</hi> is very angry that the preſent Generation ſhould pretend to know better what is fit for themſelves than the Generations paſt could poſſibly do as to a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table conſtitution, which I have anſwered already; and ſhall only add, that I believe he injures the Houſe in alledging that to be the only Reaſon they had for the Bill, That ſome Gentlemen think bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of themſelves than of their Parents; for he himſelf pretends to anſwer three more, as we ſhall hear anon: And in truth the Weſt-country Man might have been quits with him here, in a Complement almoſt of his own Coin.</p>
            <p>It being a very material Point to know how our Author came to have ſuch a Deference for his Anceſtors, he informs the <hi>Speaker</hi> thus concerning it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I was eaſily inſtructed in a Principle of Deference to the Wiſdom of our Anceſtors; and at this time I tremble when I reflect on the Correction given me by my Maſter, that I might not forget, but imitate and defend in all Times this Rule. Let them only be accounted Good, Juſt, and Wiſe Men, who regard and defend the Statutes, Laws, Ordinances and Liberties which their Fore-fathers Wiſdom and Experience obtain'd for themſelves and Poſterity. Now it is my Opinion,</hi> Mr. Speaker, <hi>that if thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who approve of this Bill, had not only been taught that Rule, but as well corrected as my ſelf, they would be of my Judgment: And I wiſh that they who depart from that Rule, and ſacrifice our Engliſh Liberties to a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Mercenary Foreigners, may not meet with a much more rigorous and exemplary Chaſtiſement from their enraged and ruined Countrymen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sum of the Matter is this, that our Author was whip'd into this Principle, and in truth it's pity but that he ſhould be whip'd out
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55812:7"/>of it again; that as he trembles when he reflects on his former Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, he might quake when he reflects on the latter. This I hope the good Readers will not think ſevere, when they conſider that our Author does not think ſuch Whipping, as he himſelf had, enough, but would plainly ſeem to wiſh for a <hi>De-Witting</hi> upon thoſe Members that were for the Bill. And for this End I conceive it was that ſuch great Bundles of his Speeches were ſent to the Silk-Weavers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Spittle-fields,</hi> that they might come and chaſtiſe the Houſe into better Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But to come to his Argument, which ſinells ſtrong indeed of his Roman Spirit; They muſt only be accounted Good, Juſt and Wiſe Men, who regard and defend the Statutes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which their Fore-fathers Wiſdom and Experience obtain'd for themſelves and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. If this be the only Rule by which we muſt try Good, Juſt, and Wiſe Men, we muſt allow it to other People and Nations as well as our ſelves: And if ſo, then other Nations have as good reaſon to put a Value upon the Wiſdom of their Anceſtors as we. And thus, if a Reformation of Religion were propos'd in <hi>Spain;</hi> No, ſay the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, they are only Good, Juſt and Wiſe Men, who regard and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Statutes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were obtain'd for us by the Wiſdom and Experience of our Fore-fathers. But the Wiſdom and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our Fore-fathers obtain'd thoſe Statutes which ſettle and eſtabliſh the Catholick Religion. <hi>Ergo,</hi> We cannot be Good, Juſt and Wiſe Men, if we admit a Reformation. And thus our Author, from his excellent Roman Spirit, hath furniſh'd the Romaniſts with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt our Religion; And if thoſe who were intruſted with the Education of our Anceſtors, for two or three Generations back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, had taken as much care to whip this Principle into their Pupils, as our Author's Tutor took to whip it into him, the World had not been troubled, as at this Day, with the peſtilent Northern Hereſy, but we had ſtill been of the <hi>old Roman and true Engliſh Spirit:</hi> And yet I'm afraid, that if the Matter be duly ſearch'd, our Author's Receipt will want a <hi>Probatum eſt;</hi> for I think there was ſufficient Care taken in the late Reigns, to whip the Nation into the Principles of Paſſive Obedience and Non-Reſiſtance, and a ſtupid ſubmiſſion to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of that Faction, who in ſpite of Senſe and Reaſon will needs be called <hi>the Church;</hi> and yet we ſee that it will not do, ſo that we muſt even imitate that Phyſician, who after he found himſelf miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in preſcribing of Bacon as an infallible Remedy againſt a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Diſtemper, becauſe he ſaw an Engliſh-man cur'd by it, qualified his <hi>Recipe</hi> with a <hi>Tantum Anglis:</hi> So muſt we infer, that this Receipt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55812:8"/>of Whipping Men into Principles, will be only ſucceſsful on thoſe of our Author's ſtamp; for no thinking-Man will be whip'd into any Principle contrary to his own Senſe and Reaſon: And thus we ſaw that neither the Degradation by the Clergy, nor the Laſhing by the <hi>Diſpenſing Judges,</hi> could whip Paſſive Obedience into Mr. <hi>Johnſon,</hi> though they laſh'd him ſoundly from <hi>Newgate</hi> to <hi>Tyburn;</hi> and yet half that Pains would have taught an Animal of our Author's kind both to fetch and carry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Arguments uſed for the Bill,</hi> (ſays my Author) <hi>are in ſubſtance theſe: Firſt, a Want of Purchaſers for our Lands; Second, of Merchants; Third, Manufacturers, who can work cheaper than the Engliſh; Fourth, Husbandmen to till the Ground. To all theſe I ſhall return ſhort Anſwers; but if I debate not on them with that Advantage and Reaſon as our Land-Admirals can (no doubt) with great Ingenuity on Sea-Politicks, I hope the Houſe will pardon me; for my Obſervation never coſt the Kingdom ſuch Expence of Money at Home and Loſſes at Sea, as hath the Experience of thoſe Honourable Perſons in Sea-Affairs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Author lays about him on all hands, and if he cannot prevail with the Silk-Weavers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from <hi>Spittle-Fields</hi> to come and chaſtiſe the Houſe with Scorpions, he's reſolv'd they ſhall feel the Scourage of his Tongue, and pours out his Vengeance upon our Land-Admirals moſt furiouſly. What pity but he himſelf had been one of them, for by his Behaviour it would ſeem that he has more than a Month's Mind to ſome Preferment, and then he may alſo learn Experience at the Nation's Coſt; for his Principles have already coſt them dear. It was obſerved to be the Method during the late Reigns, for ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as had a Mind to Court-Preferments, to inveigh bitterly againſt the Proceedings of the Court in the Houſe; and it's very probable that our Author had a Mind to try whether the ſame Methods be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable in this: and in truth, I think it were worth the Court's while, though upon no other Account but <hi>animi gratia,</hi> to put it to the Trial, that they may ſee what Mercenary Souls ſuch ſort of Men have. But if he be ſo much concern'd. at our Expence of Money at home, and our Loſſes by Sea, why is not he and his Party more active in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Cauſe, and bringing the Inſtruments to condign Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? This hath hitherto been prevented by Men of our Author's Principle, though His Majeſty gave it in charge to the Houſe. We know of what Party they were who obſtructed the Courſe of Juſtice againſt the Authors of our firſt Miſcarriages at Sea, and it's eaſie to be conjectur'd of what Side they are who hinder the diſcovery of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55812:8"/>the latter; and yet thoſe Men keep the greateſt Noiſe of any about the Loſſes of the Nation, to enrage the People againſt the preſent Government, though they themſelves be the Principal Cauſes of thoſe Loſſes, and brought this War upon us which exhauſts us with Taxes, and herein they exactly imitate the great Enemy of Mankind, who firſt Tempts and then Accuſes; and thus they lay the Government under a Neceſſity of taking ſuch and ſuch Meaſures, and imploying ſuch and ſuch Men, on pretence that the Monarchy and the Church will be otherwiſe undone, and at the ſame time throw the blame of all the Miſcarriages of their own Tools upon the Government, to make it hateful to the People, of whoſe Privileges they would now have the World to believe that they are extreamly tender, though in the former Reigns they told us, That we muſt reſign our Souls wholly to the Church, and our Bodies and Eſtates to the King, and durſt ſcarcely plead any Property in either, except we would be reputed Schiſmaticks or Traitors.</p>
            <p>But now let's come to our Author's Anſwer to the Arguments. Firſt, <hi>It's argued by ſome,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that we want Purchaſers for our Lands; this is a melancholy Conſideration. I therefore deſire thoſe Gentlemen who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of this Bill, to tell me what it is hath brought us to this Condition, That the Landed Men of</hi> England <hi>are reduc'd to ſo low an Ebb that they muſt ſell, and none left able to buy; unleſs Foreigners are naturaliz'd; Doth this prove our Forefathers wanted <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding? or doth it not rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it's occaſion'd by our Want of theirs, and not following their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples? Who never tax'd their Country to the Ruin both of themſelves and their Poſterity: Nor did they expend the Money of the Kingdom on ſuch Allies as ours; who, as we have been informed by ſome of the Privy Council, are not in our Intereſt, and will ſpare us none of their Men for our Pay without great Penſions. Likewiſe for themſelves; Can any Man hope to perſwade me that our Forefathers brought Foreign Soldiers into</hi> England <hi>and pay them, and naturalize them likewiſe, at the ſame time ſend the Engliſh Souldiers abroad to fight in a ſtrange Land without their Pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us but abate our Taxes, and after the wiſe Precedent of our Fathers, pay our own Seamen and Souldiers at home, and ſend the Foreigners back; then the Money will be found circulating at Home in ſuch Engliſhmens hands who may buy the Lands that are to be ſold, without naturalizing Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To our Author's Queſtion, what it is that hath brought us to this Condition. That Landed Men are neceſſitated to ſell, and that none are left able to buy, except Foreigners be naturaliz'd? It may be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55812:9"/>anſwered in ſhort, That the baſe Surrender, or rather betraying of our Civil and Religious Liberties in the late Reigns by thoſe of his Party, brought us to a neceſſity of inviting over our preſent Soveraign, and joining him with our Arms to recover what we had ſo loſt; and the Treachery of thoſe of his Party whom His Majeſty has been forc'd to imploy, or the Curſe of Heav'n upon ſuch Inſtruments hath many times broken his Meaſures, prolong'd the War, increas'd our Taxes, and ruin'd our Trade; but that none are left able to buy, except Foreigners be naturaliz'd, is I ſuppoſe what no body ever ſaid. There may be and are many who are able to buy that are not willing, ſo long as they ſee the Government liable to the Treachery of ſuch Men as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who would inhance the whole Adminiſtration of Affairs into their own hands, and not only exclude Foreigners, but their own Native Brethren, and a hundred times better Engliſhmen than themſelves; becauſe their Conſciences will not ſuffer them to take the Sacrament for the obtaining of a Place or Commiſſion, which they think contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our Saviour's Deſign and Inſtitution; or are not ſo ſuperlatively Proud as to pretend to a poſture of greater Humility in receiving the ſame, than was practis'd by the Holy Apoſtles; and not only for this reaſon, but alſo becauſe the Faction repreſent the honeſt and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Churchmen as not fit to be imployed, putting them almoſt in the ſame Category with Diſſenters: And therefore I would very fain know of our Author what encouragement either of thoſe ſorts of Men have to lay out their Money in buying Land, when they muſt bear equal Burden with others to ſupport the Government, while their Enemies enjoy all the profitable Imployments under it, and only watch for an opportunity, not only to deprive them of their Eſtates, as in the days of Yore, but of their Lives and all the Comforts of 'em: For we ſee ſo little of the effects of the Faction's Repentance for their having formerly perſecuted their Brethren, that on the contrary in is evident that they are ready to burſt with their Venom; which is now kept in by the Reſtraint of Law. And as to the Naturalizing of Foreigners, though we don't ſay, that none are left able to buy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that be granted; yet ſuch a Law would very much conduce to procure Chapman: For there are not only ſome French Proteſtants who are able to purchaſe, but many rich Merchants, and others in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> who would be thereby incourag'd to come and plant themſelves here, where they might have all Neceſſaries in Plenty, and the Freedom of their Religion under a Government which they love, and in a Country where they might live without any fear, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55812:9"/>from the French King, or any other Oppreſſor: and if this ſhould be the Caſe, as it probably would, conſidering the horrible Devaſtations of the Palatinat, the continual Danger of other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and elſewhere, and the little Ground that there is to be purchas'd in <hi>Holland;</hi> where, I pray, would be <hi>England</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage by an Act of Naturalization? And would it not rather be infinitely to her Advantage to have their Eſtates ſpent here upon her own Product, and her Strength increas'd by ſuch a conſiderable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Zealous Proteſtants, who know the Principles and Practices of the Papiſts ſo well, that they would be in no hazard, according to the practice of too too many of our Engliſh Proteſtants, either of eſpouſing the Intereſt of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV, the late King and his pretended Son, or of undermining the Government of Their preſent Majeſties? but this our Author and his Party know too well, and that makes 'em redouble their Clamour againſt the Act of Naturalization, though under the ſpecious pretences of an Exuberant Zeal for our Engliſh Liberties.</p>
            <p>In the next part of the Paragraph, the Gentleman charges the Houſe with ruining themſelves and their Poſterity by Taxes; as if no other of the Members had either Eſtates to be tax'd, or Poſterity to be ruin'd but himſelf. Our Author's Good Book, (for that's the higheſt Epithet which he can vouchſafe to the Holy Scriptures) ſays, He that provides not for his Family is worſe than an Infidel, an Epithet which the Moderns appropriate to the Turk: but certainly he that ruins his Family muſt be worſe, and I can't tell how to explain that better, than by ſaying, that he muſt be as bad as the French King; and ſo the Commons are obliged to this Gentleman for his Complement.</p>
            <p>Then he tells us, That our Forefathers would not expend the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Kingdom upon ſuch Allies as ours, who are not in our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and will ſpare us none of their Men for our Pay, without great Penſions likewiſe for themſelves. Here our Author runs high indeed, and brings in Privy-Counſellors to accuſe the King, as if he had made an Alliance with thoſe who are not in our Intereſt, which muſt be a very ſtrange kind of Allies indeed: I think by the Gentleman's leave, that in ſuch a cafe as this, He that is not againſt us is for us; and it's much better to have a Defenſive Alliance with the Northern Crowns than none at all, that keeps them from doing us hurt if they can do us no good; and as for their not letting us have their Men for Pay without Penſions to themſelves, if they furniſh their Quota's for their Concerns in the Empire, we have the leſs reaſon to be angry; I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55812:10"/>don't known that any Prince or State have reaſon to part with their Men, which are their Strength, for bare Pay, without any other Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration: and if His Majeſty think fit to grant it, I know no reaſon why this Gentleman ſhould caſt ſuch an Unmannerly Reflection upon it; a Provocation as ſmall as this brought <hi>Charles</hi> I. with an Armed Force to demand five Members from the Houſe of Commons: but let the King do what he can, our Author will never be pleas'd; if he ſends Engliſhmen abroad to fight, then he cries out that they are ſent to be knock's on the head without their Pay; and if he hire Foreigners, then he expends his Money upon ſuch Allies as our Forefathers would not have done, though at the ſame time His Majeſty has very few or no Allies but what at ſome time or other have been in Alliance with our Forefathers, and had of their Money too when they had not ſo much to ſpare. As to the bringing of Foreign Souldiers into <hi>England,</hi> and Naturalizing them, while at the ſame time he ſends Engliſh Souldiers abroad, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it's very hard that a Foreign Prince, who riskt his All to ſave us from being ſwallow'd up by Popery and Slavery, ſhould be denied ſome Troops of his own Countrymen for his Guards, in whom he may confide upon all Emergents: This Reflection is ſo very Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that nothing but Jacobite Impudence could have publiſh'd it; but if our Author had been a Man of Thoughts, he would have forborn this Cavil merely out of reſpect to the French King, the God of his Party, who has always Swiſs Guards about his Perſon, when natural Frenchmen are ſent abroad to ſight; and it was his Cuſtom formerly to have Scotiſh Guards too. Then as to our Engliſhmens want of Pay while Foreigners have it, it's more than I dare ſay our Author is able to inſtruct; but if he can any ways make the King odious to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he cares not by what means, ſo it be but accompliſh'd. But as to our Troops not being paid in <hi>Flanders,</hi> it's ſtrange how they come to gain Credit in that Popiſh Foreign Country without Money, and that the Natives of the Country ſhould not complain of it, which to be ſure if it were true they quickly would, and Gazettes and Letters would as quickly mention it, which ſeeing they do not, we muſt let it paſs for a Jacobite Forgery: Then as to the Naturalizing part; The number of the Foreign Souldiers which we have here is ſo very inconſiderable, that the Naturalizing of them, if they ſhould require it, would do us no damage; and it's what in Gratitude we could ſcarcely deny, that of thoſe who hazarded their Lives to ſave our Liberties, a ſmall number at leaſt ſhould partake of 'em with us. But it is not to be ſuppoſed that many of the common Souldiers will trouble
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55812:10"/>themſelves about it; and for their Officers, if they do, it adds to our Strength, and obliges them to ſpend what they ſave amongſt us; whereas otherwiſe they might carry it elſewhere: but there are not many Souldiers who are hoarders of Money; ſo that we need not be over-ſolicitous who ſhall be Heirs to their Eſtates. And in ſhort, as to the Matter of Naturalization, we need never be afraid that any other but thoſe of Eſtates will be at the Expence of coming from beyond Sea to reap the benefit of it; and if any ſuch come, they will be worth their room. But notwithſtanding all this Noiſe againſt Foreign Proteſtants, I believe there's few of the Party who would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their Sons for Apprentices, provided they may have 'em on their own terms, and then they muſt be Enfranchis'd whether they will or not; ſo that it's plain, that this Spite againſt Foreign Proteſtants flows not from any Damage that their Naturalization can do us, but merely becauſe they are firm to the Government. Then as to the ſending of Men to <hi>Flanders,</hi> that is a mighty Grievance to our Author. The <hi>Netherlands</hi> have been formerly thought our Barrier, the ſecuring of them was the ſecuring of our Selves; ſo that it's no wonder he ſhould be angry that we ſend Men thither, becauſe it gives the French King ſuch a Diverſion, that he has no leiſure to reſtore the late King: and could Monſieur but once ſecure ſome good Harbours in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for his Men of War, he would very quickly make us a Viſit, and as ſpeedily ruine our Proteſtant Allies the Dutch; which would mightily rejoice our Author's Heart: For it's eaſie to perceive that he cares not though the War were in our own Bowels, when he is not willing that we ſhould meet the Enemy beyond Sea and keep him at Home: And that we may be further-convinc'd of his Good Will to the Nation, he preſſes hard for the Abatement of our Taxes. If the Caſe would admit it, I believe that every body would be glad of it as well as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but if the Taxes be abated, how ſhall the War be maintain'd, and not only our Honour, but our Religion and Liberties be ſecur'd? If <hi>England</hi> ſhould fall off, the League would quickly diſſolve, the French King would ſpeedily gain his Point, and make us pay more in one Year by his Military Contributions, than we have done yet during the War; he would take care to put us out of a Condition to trouble him any more beyond Sea, to caſt the ballance of <hi>Europe,</hi> or maintain the Proteſtant Religion abroad; and as he hath had no Mercy on his own Country, we have no reaſon to expect he ſhould have any on ours: and yet our Author muſt ſet up for a Grand Patriot to his Country, becauſe of his Noble Speech, adviſing us to withdraw our hand from that which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55812:11"/>we had better never have begun, than to leave unfiniſh'd; for the Caſe is come now to this Point, that either we muſt render the French King uncapable of troubling his Neighbours any more, which (bleſſed be God) his Majeſty is in a fair way of effecting, or elſe we muſt follow his Triumphal Chariot, and inſtead of our Liberties, hug our Chains.</p>
            <p>Our Author's next Advice is, <hi>To pay our own Seamen and Souldiers at Home, and ſend the Foreigners back; Then will the Money circulate at Home in ſuch Engliſh-mens Hands, who may buy the Lands that are to be ſold,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here's ſomewhat to do about paying our Souldiers: but he would do well to acquaint us by what way it may be effected, without the Taxes which he is for abating. And whether it be the King's Fault that they are not paid? Had the Arrears of his Army been as long unpaid, as the Victuals and Clothes of K. <hi>Ch.</hi> II: Had he ſpent his Money as he did, upon Ladies of Pleaſure, and maintaining B—ds: Had he ſhut up the Exchequer, or defrauded his Creditors; or had he refuſed to give the Nation an Account of their Money, there had been ſome ground for this Clamour. But if any of our Author's Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or of the high-Church-Faction, have miſapply'd the Money which was deſign'd for that End, why do not our Murmurers concur to bring them to puniſhment? I am confident they may have the King's Leave. As for the ſending of the few Foreign Troops which we have back, I have touch'd upon the Ingratitude of that already. And as to the paying of our Sea-men and Souldiers at Home, the former are never paid any where elſe; and for the latter, we had better pay them in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to keep the French at a Diſtance, than expoſe our ſelves to a French Invaſion by withdrawing them, for in that Caſe we muſt pay them and the French both: And for the few Foreign-Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers which we have among us, I'm ſure they have neither their Clothes nor their Victuals from <hi>Holland,</hi> and therefore their Pay muſt needs circulate in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Author goes on thus. <hi>Secondly, It's ſaid we want more Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants: Whom may we thank for bringing ſo many to Poverty? But I ſhall forbear grating, and deſire the Liberty to conſider in ſhort how the Trade of</hi> England <hi>hath hitherto been carried on. Gentlemen have placed their youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Children to Merchants. Their Maſters obſerving their Honeſty and Diligence, when they have gained ſome Experience in the neceſſary Parts of Trade, generally ſend them Abroad, to</hi> Turky, <hi>all Parts of the</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>to</hi> Spain, Portugal, Eaſt <hi>and</hi> Weſt-Indies; <hi>and all Parts where</hi> England <hi>holds any conſiderable Commerce, there the young Men are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55812:11"/>by, and entruſted with the Stocks and Eſtate of their Maſters and Friends, whereby all Parties, both the Principals at Home, and the Factors Abroad, are advantaged, and</hi> England <hi>enriched, (for therein end all Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters); and at laſt, when they are ſatiated with Gain, they return to their Native Soil, their Friends and Relations, for Eaſe and Enjoyment, making room for a younger Generation to ſucceed in their profitable Employments. Thus hitherto this Kingdom hath advanc'd in Riches, whilſt Foreigners could not with Succeſs plant their Factories on us through the Advantage we had by our Laws. Let us but turn the Tables, and conſider the Conſequence; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we paſs this Bill, and the</hi> Dutch (<hi>who no doubt will take the Oaths as this Bill directs to, and proteſt againſt Popery and Paganiſm, and on occaſion Chriſtianity too, as at</hi> Japan) <hi>ſend their Servants and Factors hither, and we naturalize them, and let the Capital Stock, which gets an Employ to theſe new-made Engliſh-men, belong to their Maſters and Friends, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, or ever will live amongst us: Will it not then follow that the Profit will be theirs, and not</hi> England's? <hi>And will not the new-made Engliſh (yet Dutch-men ſtill) return to their Countrey and Friends with their Gain, as our People hitherto have done? We may obſerve by our Inland Trade, that it's ſeldom they who made the Manufacturies gain Eſtates, but thoſe who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their Stocks in buying and ſelling what others made. And it's the ſame with the Merchants, thoſe that Export and Import are the Gainers; the firſt Maker very ſeldom, the Conſumptioner never.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Concluſion then of this Experiment muſt be this, That what hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been Gain to</hi> England, <hi>by Engliſh Merchants and Factors, will be turn'd to a Foreign Land by the Foreign Merchants, naturaliz'd for their own Good, not</hi> England's.</p>
            <p>Here's a long Paragraph, but little to the Purpoſe. As to our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Queſtion, Whom we may thank for bringing ſo many of our Merchants to Poverty? It may eaſily be anſwered, Even thoſe of his Stamp, who give the <hi>French</hi> notice of all our Motions by Sea; or being entruſted with the Management of our convoys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let them fall into the Enemy's Hand, either by Treachery or Cowardiſe. Then as to the Return of our Factors from <hi>Turky, Spain, Portugal;</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> &amp;c. with Riches to themſelves and Maſters, after they were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated with Gain, it muſt be obvious to every Man that thoſe Factors bought the Product of thoſe Countries where they were imploy'd, and liv'd upon the ſame while there: So that our Money for the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts did circulate in thoſe Countries, or at leaſt that which was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to Money in Value; and conſequently were profitable to thoſe Countries as well as to our own, both by exporting their Product, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55812:12"/>imploying the Natives in the ſeveral Manufactures, Carriage by Land and Water. And in the ſame manner may we reap Advantage by Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Proteſtant Factors, and yet Expedients found out, by the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Parliament, to ſecure our own Trade by Exportation. But further, I would enquire of our Author, whether he thinks there's no difference betwixt Foreign Proteſtants living here, and Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants living amongſt Pagans, Turks and Papiſts, in ſuch Places where neither the Climate, Religion nor Conſtitutions of the Country are agreeable to them, eſpecially if they be ſuch as have any Zeal for their Religion; I ſay, I would fain know if it be not much more probable to think that our Plenty of good Proviſions, the Pleaſantneſs of our Countrey, Healthfulneſs of our climate, together with the Whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſs of our conſtitutions and firm Eſtabliſhment of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, without fear of Oppreſſion by Potent Neighbours, are not like to be more powerful Attractives to induce Foreign Proteſtants to ſettle here, than any thing that can be found in thoſe Countries which our Author has nam'd, to induce Engliſh-men to ſettle there, eſpecially when thoſe Proteſtants are Naturaliz'd? But our Author's Rancour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> hath ſo much blinded both the Eyes of his Body and Soul, that he can neither ſee nor conſider, that it were an eaſy Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Parliament to provide againſt all thoſe Inconveniencies, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or Imaginary, which he hath heap'd together, and yet make an Act of Naturalization, not only profitable to our ſelves, but advantageous to Foreign Proteſtants, without planting their Factories on us, ſo as to ruin our own Trade, or permitting thoſe who ſhall raiſe Eſtates in this Kingdom, to go and ſpend them elſewhere. And it had been much more deſerving the Title of a Patriot, which our Author is ſo fond of, if he had modeſtly propounded his Objections, and deſired the Houſe to conſider of thoſe ſuppoſed Inconveniencies, than to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel the Repreſentatives of the Nation by Seditious Pamphlets, to bring them under a general Odium by the People whom they repreſent at Home, and in hazard of their Lives by the Silk-Weavers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> here.</p>
            <p>As to his Reflections on the <hi>Dutch,</hi> for denying their Religion at <hi>Japan;</hi> Envy and Spite will make us look at our Neighbours Faults through a Magnifying-Glaſs, or find Faults where there are none. I know that in <hi>Charles</hi> Il's Time, when it was thought fit, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the Proteſtant Intereſt, to deſtroy our Proteſtant Neighbours the <hi>Dutch,</hi> all the Calumnies that Malice could invent were publiſh'd againſt them, and this amongſt others. But what if it be true? why ſhould all the <hi>Dutch</hi> be chargeable with this, more than all Engliſh-men
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55812:12"/>are chargeable with the Renegado's of their own Nation, who fall off to Popery and Mahumetaniſm but too frequently?</p>
            <p>Our Author continues thus. <hi>But this is not all, for at once the Art of Navigation will be rendered uſeleſs; whence then will be a Nurſery for Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon? for Foreign Merchants will naturalize Foreign Seamen: and when the Preſs-maſters find them, they will</hi> Dutcher ſpreaking, ye Min-heer, <hi>and avoid the Service. But at the Cuſtom-Houſe, Exchange, and in all Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they will be found as good Engliſh-men as any be of this Houſe; from whence it followeth that Trade will be only carried on by Foreign Merchants and Seamen, and the Engliſh Seamen condemned to our Men of War, and perhaps live there as hitherto, without their Pay, till another Million be ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them for Wages; and in the interim have this only Conſolation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for Service done, and to be done, that their Wives and Children may be ſubſisted by the Alms of the Pariſh, whilſt Foreign Souldiers are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd at Home and Abroad with their Pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Gentleman thinks he has hit the White, and that ſurely the Nation will never have any more regard to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who would render their Navigation uſeleſs, by which we have increas'd our Wealth and our Glory: but the height of our author's Paſſion wont let him ſee his own Inconſiſtencies: I hope if the Foreign Seamen be once Naturaliz'd, their ſpeaking Dutch won't exempt them from the King's Service; and any Man of half our Author's Invention, may find an Expedient how the Preſs-Maſters ſhall know whether they be Naturaliz'd or not; and if this be done, then we ſhall be able to provide our Fleet with more eaſe than at preſent, when we cannot only Impreſs our own Native Seamen, but our Naturaliz'd Foreigners. As for our Seamens want of their Pay, while their Families are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by Alms, it hath been ſufficiently anſwered already; and if the Cauſes were truly inquir'd into, and the Inſtruments duly puniſh'd, I am afraid that ſome of our Author's Stamp would paſs their time but very ſorrily. Then as to the maintaining of Foreign Souldiers at Home, their Number is ſo very few, and every Day like to grow leſs, that there is more of Malice than any thing elſe in the Objection. And for thoſe we maintain Abroad, there are the more of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men ſav'd, not only from the Fury of the Sword, but the raging Diſtempers of the Camp, which generally proves fatal to great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, till they be once ſeaſon'd: but our peeviſh Author can no ways be pleas'd; he's angry that Engliſh-men ſhould be ſent Beyond-Sea, and yet will neither let his Majeſty have Foreign Souldiers at Home nor Abroad.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:55812:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Third Argument,</hi> ſays this worthy Knight, <hi>for admitting of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, is upon a ſuppoſed want we have of Manufacturers, eſpecially ſuch as will work cheaper than the Engliſh. In my Opinion, this Reaſoning is Extraordinary, and ought not to take Air out of the Houſe, leſt the old Engliſh spirit ſhould exert it ſelf in Defence of its Liberties; for at this time when all Proviſions are become exceſſive dear by the great Quantities exported to</hi> Holland, <hi>which puts the poor Engliſh Manufacturers on Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in moſt Parts of</hi> England, <hi>for want of a full Imployment to enable them to ſupport their Families by their honeſt and painful Labour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, ſhall an Engliſh Parliament let in Strangers to under-ſell our Country, which they may eaſily do whilſt they live in Garrets, pay no Taxes, and are bound to no Duty? How ſhall we anſwer this to our Country who ſent us here? when by ſo doing, inſtead of making the Kingdom more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, we provide only for the Subſiſtance of Foreigners, and put our Countrymen to the Choice of ſtarving at home, or to turn Souldiers and be ſent to</hi> Flanders, <hi>and ſtarve there for want of their Pay; for it's well known that at this time more Commodities are made in</hi> England <hi>than can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd a broad or at home, which makes the poor Manufacturers ſo miſerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That there are ſeveral Manufactures which we us'd to import from <hi>France</hi> and elſewhere in time of Peace, becauſe we could neither have them made ſo cheap nor ſo well in <hi>England,</hi> is what I think no body can deny; and if by Naturalizing French and Dutch Proteſtants, we can have thoſe Manufactures made as cheap here as they had them there, and cheaper and better than the few that make them in <hi>England</hi> can do, will not the Good of the whole be more than a ſufficient Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation for the loſs of a few, which may alſo be provided againſt by the Wiſdom of the Parliament, either by incorporating our own with the Foreign Manufacturers, and making them the Managers or Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of the ſame if capable, or by ſuch other Methods as the Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this Bill and the Prudence of the Houſe ſhall ſuggeſt: and by this means, will not the Money which us'd to be exported for thoſe Commodities be ſpent and circulate at home, and the Foreigners who now live meanly and in Garrets, to avoid the Sowre becauſe they muſt reap none of the Sweet, be encourag'd and enabl'd to live after a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rate, marry and ſet up Families, (whereas now many of them live ſingle becauſe of their Poverty) pay Houſe-Rent and Taxes, wear better Apparel, and ſpend more liberally in Houſekeeping; by which Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod the fruits of their Labours will circulate to the remoteſt Corners of the Kingdom, and the Nation become fuller of People, who will help to ſpend the Commodities made in <hi>England,</hi> which our Author
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55812:13"/>ſays are more than can be conſum'd either at Home or Abroad, and occaſions the Miſery of our Manufacturers: and if the Dutch teach us their way of making Linen, and the French theirs of making Paper, will not great Sums which are continually returned beyond Sea for thoſe Commodities, be ſpent at Home? So that we may eaſily perceive our Author's Clamour againſt the Houſe to be very unreaſonable, and his Suggeſtion of the danger of their Arguments taking Air without Doors extremely Malicious, and altogether the Product of his J—ite Roman Spirit, which prompted him to ſend his Libels amongſt thoſe that he thought would be the moſt eaſily impos'd upon by them, in hopes (as is manifeſt from his hint of the old Engliſh Spirit's exerting it ſelf in defence of its Liberties, which plainly points at former In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections againſt Foreigners) to procure an Uproar; which as it would have endangered the Parliament, diſturb'd the Peace of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and given the Jacobites an opportunity of acting under a diſguiſe, would have alſo prevented His Majeſty's going beyond Sea himſelf, or ſending his Forces thither, and by conſequence have promoted <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV's and the late King's Intereſt; and no doubt our Author's miſcarrying in this Attempt, will afford new matter of Reflection to the <hi>Paris</hi> Gazetteer, like that which he had in his Gazette of the 6th of <hi>March,</hi> That thoſe Members of the Houſe who are for the Publick Good have not been ſucceſsful in their Endeavours againſt the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners; for I queſtion not but our Author has taken care to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his Efforts to the Court at <hi>St. Germains,</hi> and his Libel will make the French believe that <hi>England</hi> is in as bad a Condition as <hi>France.</hi> Then s to his Malicious Reflection on the Members for the Bill, that they take care for the Subſiſtance of Foreigners, and put our own Countrymen to the Choice of Starving at home, or turning Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and be ſent to <hi>Flanders</hi> to ſtarve there for want of Pay; it's like the Charity of his Faction, who when the poor French Proteſtants fled hither from the tyrannous Perſecution at home, would force them to a Compliance with things contrary to their Conſciences here, or elſe they muſt ſtarve. But if our Author bad not been in a mighty haſte to produce his J—ite Birth to the World, he might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that when Foreigners are Naturalized, they are liable to bear Arms either at home or abroad, as the Exigence of the Government requires, as much as Engliſhmen: Nor is it to be ſuppoſed that the Parliament would ever be ſo unnatural, as he would wickledly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them, to feed Foreigners and ſtarve their own Countrymen. I believe there's none who will think that Sir <hi>J. K.</hi> alone has all the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55812:14"/>Bowels of Compaſſion for his Country, and that the reſt of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have none. This pretended Zeal for the People, is but like the Jack-daw's counterfeit Dreſs of Pigeon's Feathers, that he might the better get into the Dove-houſe to deſtroy the Eggs and the Young; but being once diſcovered by his Cawing, that he was not a Pigeon of the right kind, the reſt expell'd him the Dove-houſe; and it's pity, as was ſaid by an ingenious Member, that if this be Sir <hi>J. K</hi>'s Cawing, but he ſhould undergo the ſame fate. This outragious Clamour, all Circumſtances being conſidered, looks very like ſuch a Signal as that which a Frenchman, of whom I have read, gave to one of the <hi>Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who had been driven from his Throne for Male-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, that he might venture to attempt the recovery of it again: and I wiſh that our Author, and ſome others, may not be of that Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor's Kidney, who run out into a mighty Zeal againſt the depoſed <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> till he had run his Succeſſor into the ſame Meaſures for which he was depos'd, fruſtrated or retarded his Deſigns; whereby he forc'd him to make his Government grievous to the People by hard Taxes, and then by exclaiming againſt his Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, pav'd the Way for <hi>Childerick</hi>'s return<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mezeray</hi>'s Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Then our Author proceeds thus, <hi>All Country Gentlemen within this Houſe, have for ſeveral Seſſions laboured what they could to raiſe the Price of the Proviſions which their Lands produce, and ſome think it not great enough yet, and they would deſpiſe that Man who ſhould endeavour to lower the Rates by propoſing a free Importation of Iriſh Cattle and Corn, though he had no other Deſign, than that Charitable and Neceſſary one of relieving the Poor; and yet theſe very Gentlemen are for this Bill, becauſe they would have the Labour of the Poor brought to a lower Advantage. In my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, this is a very unequal way of reaſoning, that whilſt we raiſe the Price of the Product of the Land, for the Gentlemen to live in a greater ſtate, at the ſame time our Conſults are how to make the half-ſtarv'd Manufactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers that live by their daily Labour, more and more miſerable. What Opinion will the common People of</hi> England <hi>have of this Houſe and the Gentlemen of the Kingdom, whom nothing can pleaſe but what is made by Foreigners, or comes from Abroad?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That none of the Members may eſcape our Author's Fury, and that of his Party, he takes care to accuſe firſt <hi>All</hi> the Country Gentlemen, and then all the reſt; the firſt of ſtarving the Poor to keep up the price of the Proviſions which their Lands produce, and hindering the Importation of Iriſh Corn and Cattle for the Relief of the Poor, becauſe they would have their Labour brought to a lower Advantage, and then
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55812:14"/>all the reſt, of conſulting how to make our half-ſtarv'd Manufacturers more miſerable: Can any Man whoſe Charity is of the largeſt ſize, look upon this way of Libelling any otherwiſe than as the ſounding of an Alarm to ſuch Tumults as thoſe of <hi>Jack Straw</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyler</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, and calculated on purpoſe to make the poor Labourers and Tradeſmen not only knock all the Members of Parliament, but all the Gentry of the Kingdom on the head; that ſo during our Confuſions, the late King's Party might declare for him, now that the Spring is advancing apace, and the Jacobite Humours all afloat? So that though we cannot tell this Gentleman what opinion the common People will have of the Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet we are ſure they can have none worſe than what he endeavours to inſpire them with, but all in vain; as is ſeen by the Event, and the Silk-Weavers bringing in his bundles of Libels to be burnt in the Flames; by which it appears that the Pigeons have diſcovered the Jack-daw by his Cawing.—But if there be any of the Members ſo criminally Uncharitable as he repreſents them, may the Juſtice of Heav'n and the Nation find them out: It had been more like a Patriot and a good Countryman to have expoſtulated the caſe modeſtly with them, than to enrage the Poor and ſet them on to worry them, though very undeſervedly, conſidering the Kindneſs which they have ſhewed to our own Manufacturers, both by an Act for Importing Italian Silk, and the care they have taken to improve the Woollen Manufactures.</p>
            <p>To return to our Author, he ſays further, <hi>That our Palats for a long time have been ſo nice, that nothing but a French Cook could pleaſe: nor could we perſwade our ſelves that our Clothing was good, unleſs from head to foot we were</hi> A-la-mode de France. <hi>The Gentleman was not well ſerved without a Frenchman, and the Lady's Commode could not ſit right, if her fine French Woman did not put it on. Now of a ſudden the Change is as violent in favour of the Dutch, who are great Courtiers, and the only taking-People, and our Engliſh are a ſort of Clumſy-fiſted People, if compared with the Dutch</hi> Hans <hi>and</hi> Fro; <hi>and in ſhort, the Engliſhmen are fit for nothing but to be ſent to</hi> Flanders, <hi>and there either to fight, ſteal, or ſtarve for want of Pay. There is one thing, Mr.</hi> Speaker, <hi>which comes into my Mind, with which I ſhall cloſe this Conſideration, What reaſon was there for blaming the Mayors, Aldermen, Common-Councils, and other Governors of Corporations for Surrendring the Charters, though they ſtill retain the Rights for Engliſhmen only to come into new Charters, and at the ſame time hope to juſtify our Proceedings, though we throw up the Great Charter of our Engliſh Liberties, to admit Strangers?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:55812:15"/>
            <p>The Gentleman's Reflections on the French, are juſt like the ſhort Clauſe againſt Papiſts that us'd to be in King <hi>Charles</hi> Il's long Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations againſt Proteſtant diſſenters, which came merely in as words of courſe; and though I ſhall be far from defending our Apiſh Imitation of the French in their Garb, yet I think it much leſs Criminal than to covet their Government, as it's but too too apparent our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor does by his Concern, that the Surrender of Charters ſhould be condemned, which would have brought us to the Bleſſings of Arbitrary Government in a trice, and have ſav'd our Kings the trouble of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; for then they might have had a Houſe of Commons of their own making, to have ſuted a Houſe of Lord's of <hi>Charles</hi> Il's begetting, and a Church of <hi>Caſſander</hi> or Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi>'s Conſtitution: Nor is our Author any happier in his Compariſon betwixt the Surrender of our Charters and the Bill of Naturalization, than in his Hiſtory of the Dutch being as much in Vogue for Courtiers with our nice Palats now, as the French were in former times; though if it were ſo, I am of opinion that no ſolid Men, nor good Proteſtants, would be ſorry at the Change. But we ſhall have ſomewhat more to ſay to him anon as to his Treatment of the Dutch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Fourth Pretence for this Bill,</hi> (ſays my Author) <hi>is a want of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen to till the Ground. I ſhall ſay little on this Head, but requeſt the Honourable Perſon below, me to tell me of the</hi> 40000 <hi>French which he confeſſeth are come into</hi> England, <hi>How many does he know that at this time follow the Plough-tail; for it is my firm Opinion, that not only the French, but any other nation this Bill ſhall let in upon us, will never tranſplant them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the benefit of going to Plough, they will contentedly leave the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the ſole Monopoly of that Slavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This worthy Knight may pleaſe to conſider, that abundance of thoſe French would be glad to follow the Plough-tail in <hi>England,</hi> if their Languge and other circumſtances would but admit it, rather than be in the ſtarving Condition that many of 'em labour under. Such of them as have been Farmers, are neither acquainted with our way of Manuring, nor have they Stock or Credit to procure Farms; moſt of them have been brought up in another way of living; for it's ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently known, that the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> had the greateſt part of the Trade and Manufactures in the Nation. Many of them are Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Officers and Scholars, and conſequently unfit for ſuch an Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and our Farmers have not commonly ſo much reſpect for the meaner ſort of them, as to make uſe of their Service either for Plough or Cart; and for ſuch as would come hither to reap the benefit of being
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55812:15"/>naturaliz'd, it's probable, that they may be Perſons of better condition than ordinary Farmers, and their Stocks might be more advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly imployed in the Kingdom; while at the ſame time the increaſe of People will require an increaſe of Proviſions, and by conſequence make Farming and Plowing both more frequent and profitable than it is at preſent.</p>
            <p>Our Author's next Paragraph is thus: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the whole, Sir, it's my Judgment, that ſhould this bill paſs, it will bring as great Afflictions on this Nation as ever fell upon the Egyptians; and one of their Plagues we have at this time very ſevere upon us, I mean that of their Land bringing forth Frogs in abundance, even in the Chambers of their Kings; for there is no entring the Courts of</hi> St. James's <hi>and</hi> Whitehall, <hi>the Palaces of our Hereditary Kings, for the great Noiſe and Croaking of the Frog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, ſo long as we have ſo many hard-hearted <hi>Pharaohs</hi> as our Author and his Party, who do ſo much oppreſs their Native, and ſo maliciouſly revile their Foreign Proteſtant Brethren, we have reaſon enough to dread the Plagues of <hi>Egypt;</hi> for our Author and his Faction, who did ſo violently perſecute diſſenting Proteſtants in the late Reigns, eſpecially at <hi>B—l,</hi> are ſtill very unwilling to let them go; and all that our <hi>Moſes</hi> hath hitherto been able to procure for his oppreſſed Brethren at the hand of theſe <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> is, that they may go and ſerve God as they pleaſe, but they muſt leave all the Places of Power and Profit to them: juſt like the Liberty that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> gave to the Iſraelites, that they might go and ſacrifice to God in the Wilderneſs; but they muſt leave their Flocks and Stocks behind 'em. And now that the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians of <hi>Scotland</hi> are quite eſcap'd, and the Diſſenters in Old and New <hi>England</hi> enjoy their Liberty, our Author and his Party are ſo eager to be up and after them, that nothing will be able to put a ſtop to their Career, but ſome ſuch remarkable Judgment as the drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Egyptians in the Red Sea.—</p>
            <p>As to our Author's Scurrilities upon the Dutch, they are but the poor efforts of an unmanly, impotent, and unbridled Paſſion, and ſuch as bring more diſgrace on himſelf than the worſt he intends to them: For, if we conſider them either as part of the antient <hi>Belgae,</hi> they have been famous in all Hiſtory; or if we conſider them as the old <hi>Batavi,</hi> they are no leſs Renowned; if we take them as a Colony of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, as undoubtedly they are, then they are of the ſame Original with our ſelves; and therefore ought not to contemn them. Whatever difference the ſituation of their Country and way of Living may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55812:16"/>in the Lineaments of their Bodies, or whatever difference their form of Government makes betwixt their Cuſtoms and ours, yet that the predominant part of our Language is from the ſame Radix with theirs, there's no Man who knows the one and the other that can doubt; and that this is one of the beſt Arguments to prove a People to be of the ſame Original, the greateſt of Antiquaries will allow: but if we conſider the Dutch, as having gallantly ſtruggled with, and as glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly overcome the Power and Pride of the Spaniards, who were Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors to the French in their Enmity to the Proteſtant Religion and Common Liberties of <hi>Europe,</hi> there's no Encomium high enough for them; and if we will give our ſelves leave to conſider to what a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious height of Power and Greatneſs they have rais'd their Country in ſo ſhort a time under the fortunate Auſpices of the Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> ſince the Reformation began to dawn amongſt them, and how they have hitherto been as a Buſh burning and not conſumed, though ſeveral times ſet on fire by French Papiſts, and our Author's ſort of Proteſtants, under the Conduct of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and <hi>Charles</hi> II. we can look upon them as no leſs than the Darlings of Heaven, and a People over whom Providence hath had a peculiar Care, thereby to make them the Inſtruments of doing great things in the World, ſuch as the effecting of our ſtupendous Revolution, by which they grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully repaid us for the Aſſiſtance which they received from our glorious Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and for which we owe to them and our Gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, their Stadtholder and General, the Preſervation under God of all that is dear to us as Engliſhmen and Proteſtants: but I know that all theſe Topicks of Commendation is a ſacrificing the Abomination of our Author and the reſt of his Egyptian Faction in their own ſight; and therefore ſhall come nearer him thus. I wonder how they who pretend to adore the Memory of the two <hi>Charles's,</hi> dare thus treat a People to whoſe Stadtholder and General the Firſt married his eldeſt Daughter, and the Second his Neece, and alſo the eldeſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the late King; Matches which the Emperour himſelf would have been proud of: Or how thoſe who pretend to be Men of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, can ſpeak ſo deſpicably of a People who have been honoured with a Race of the greateſt Hero's for Princes that the latter Ages have ſeen. But let the Faction treat this People as they pleaſe, and eſteem them as Frogs, or what elſe their Malice can invent; for my own part, if it be ſo, I will declare my ſelf a Proteſtant <hi>Ranelite</hi> on their account, as thinking my ſelf under as great an Obligation to reverence and eſteem theſe Dutch Frogs, ſince they muſt be ſo call'd,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55812:16"/>for plaguing our Author's beloved Kings, and infeſting the Chambers and Houſes of them and their Egyptian Faction, as ever the Jewiſh Sect called <hi>Ranelites,</hi> thought themſelves bound to reverence thoſe Frogs which plagu'd <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his court: and that which ſhall heighten my Reverence is, that from amongſt theſe Froglanders, as he calls them, we have now not only an Hereditary King, but one whom God and the good People of <hi>England</hi> have choſen; though I doubt not but to our Worthy Knight and Men of his ſtamp, the noiſe of the Locuſts, or the Prieſts and Jeſuits which were formerly hatch'd in the Chambers of our Kings, was a much more Melodious Muſick than that which he calls <hi>the Croaking of the Dutch Frogs:</hi> and thus I chaſtiſe our Author's Contempt, becauſe the baſeſt are always ready to deſpiſe the beſt; and as our Author's Sirname would denote him of Dutch Original, and his Extract to be from the meaneſt of their People, it's no wonder that he ſhould thus deſpiſe a Nation where his Predeceſſors were never above the ſphere of an Ordinary Servant; and ſo much his Name will tell him, let him ſearch for the Etymology when he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>Our Author in the next place goes on thus: <hi>Mr.</hi> Speaker, <hi>This Nation is a Religious, Juſt and Zealous Nation, who in ſome of their Fits and Zeal, have not only quarrelled and fought for the ſame, but have murder'd and depos'd Kings, Nobles, Biſhops and Prieſts for the ſake of their Religion and Liberty, which they pretend to prove from the Bible; We are the Religious Repreſentatives of this Religious People: Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore learn Inſtruction in this caſe before us from that Good Book, where we may be inform'd, that St.</hi> Paul <hi>by being born Free of Heathen</hi> Rome, <hi>eſcap'd a Whipping, and valued and pleaded that Privilege; and the Chief Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the</hi> Romans <hi>prides himſelf, that he with a great Sum obtain'd that Freedom, and fear'd greatly when he violated St.</hi> Paul's <hi>Liberty, only by binding of him: and ſhall we ſet at nought the Freedom of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Nation, who are a Religious Chriſtian Kingdom, and part with the ſame to Strangers for nothing unleſs the undoing of our own Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who ſent us here, but not on this Errand? Certainly we ſhould follow the Example of the Roman Captain, and fear and tremble when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the just Provocation we give to the Kingdom, who will expect that we preſerve, and not deſtroy every Engliſhman's private Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the worthy Knight begins to pull off his Mask and declare himſelf openly, and if it had not been altogether a Layman's Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue, we might juſtly have reckon'd it the Second Part of Dr. <hi>Birch</hi>'s
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55812:17"/>Sermon, for which it's probable he expected Thanks. Our Author ſhows himſelf to have a mighty Veneration for our Religion, when he charges it with the murdering and depoſing of Kings. This looks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed like ſomewhat of the Reſentments of a <hi>Roman Spirit,</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd on our Religion, becauſe we juſtly charge ſuch Practices upon the Romaniſts, as the natural reſult of theirs; and this Spirit of his is further incens'd, that we pretend to prove our Religion from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but if he pleaſes to peruſe the Debates <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> about the depoſing of the late King, for he's all that has been depos'd, ſince we durſt be ſo bold as to bring Arguments from the Bible, he will find the lawfulneſs of that Practice to be ſufficiently proved from thence; but perhaps that may leſſen his eſteem of the Bible, which now, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, he thinks may be call'd a <hi>Good Book;</hi> tho it had been no Hyperbole in one who reckons himſelf a Proteſtant, to have call'd it the beſt of Books. Then as to the Inſtructions which we may have from this <hi>Good Book</hi> of his, to value our Engliſh Liberties as much as the Romans did theirs; we heartily agree to them, and eſpecially ſeeing he muſt needs allow from his own Argument, that this <hi>Juſt and Religious Nation</hi> was not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> and <hi>Irreligious</hi> in proving their Liberties from the Bible: And now that he has drawn one Inſtruction thence, we hope that he will give us liberty to draw another, and that is, that thoſe Romans, whom he propoſes to us as a Pattern, did not only allow Strangers, ſuch as St. <hi>Paul</hi> who was a Jew, to have a ſhare of their Privileges, but did alſo fell them on occaſion, as here to this Captain whom our Author mentions; and I hope as he propoſes the wiſe Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> for a Pattern to us in the one, he will alſo allow us the liberty to imitate them in the other. And thus our Author hath condemned himſelf out of his own Mouth, and given a very good Argument for Naturalizing of Foreign Proteſtants; and hence we perceive the Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of honeſt Dame Nature, which hath ordered it ſo, that many times the moſt Venomous Animals carry their own Antidote with them. And I would fain know of our Author, why we may not as well make an Act for a General Naturalization, as naturalize Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners by Fifty at a time? And whether it were not more generous for the true Engliſh Spirit to exceed the old Roman Spirit of ſelling their Privileges by granting them to Foreign Proteſtants freely? But I am afraid that Sir <hi>J</hi>'s making mention of the Captain's having bought this Freedom, will be interpreted by ſome as if he in particular expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a Bribe from Foreign Proteſtants; for we know the beſt way of ſtopping the Mouths of ſome is to give <hi>offam Cerbero.</hi> Before I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55812:17"/>abſolve this Paragraph, I muſt take notice that this pretended <hi>Atlas</hi> of our Engliſh Liberties, founds the Alarm once more to a Rebellion, by inſinuating ſuch Cauſes of Terror as had the Commons been faint-hearted, might have made them all run out of the Houſe, and then Sir <hi>J.</hi> might have had the Ball at his Foot, and kick'd the Bill our after them: But for all his Clamour, we find that his Counrymen whom he courts ſo much to a Tumult, cannot ſee thoſe frightful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences that attend this Bill, except our Author will be pleas'd to lend them his J—ite Spectacles; the one of which I ſuppoſe to be a Magnifying, and the other a Multiplying-Glaſs.</p>
            <p>But our kind Author gives us another Leſſon thus: <hi>Sir, we may further learn from that Book the Fate of the Egyptians, who experimented on the ſcore of Charity, what it is People may expect from admitting Strangers into their Country and Councils;</hi> Joſeph <hi>was a Stranger ſold a Slave into</hi> Egypt, <hi>yet being taken into</hi> Pharaoh's <hi>Council, he by Taxes and other fine Projects, brought the ſeven Years Plenty that God had bleſſed</hi> Egypt <hi>with, into the Granaries of</hi> Pharaoh; <hi>but when a Dearth came on the Land, and the People cried to their King for Relief, they were ſent to the Stranger</hi> Joſeph, <hi>who getteth from them for that which was once all their own, their Money, their Cattle, their Lands, and laſt of all their Perſons into Slavery; though at the ſame time he did far otherwiſe by his own Countrymen, for he plac'd them in the beſt of the Land, the Land of</hi> Goſhen, <hi>and nouriſh'd them from the King's Stores. This Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould teach us to be wiſe in time, ſeeing all this was done by the Advice of one Foreigner in Privy Council; and what may that Country expect where the Head and many of the Council are Foreigners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may perceive that our Author is now drawing near a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe he reſerv'd the ſharpeſt Sting for the Tail: But it's a Queſtion, whether he be more prophane in playing thus with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than falſe in miſapplying it? for it's plain, that it was no Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to <hi>Joſeph</hi> which made <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the Egyptians advance him, but Charity to themſelves, becauſe they could not find a Man ſo fit as himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.38. in whom the Spirit of God was, to find out Means to prevent the ill Conſequences of the Famine which the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God had foretold him of. And if this do not border on Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, to call the Suggeſtions of the Holy Spirit to prevent the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, not only of the Egyptians, but the peculiar People of God, Taxes, and other fine Projects to bring the Plenty of <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Granaries; I ſubmit it to the Judgment, not only of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, but of all Men who have any true Senſe of Religion: And if
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55812:18"/>this Odious Character which he gives of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> as having trick'd the Egyptians into Slavery, be not contrary to that Character given of him by the Holy Ghoſt, when he is reckon'd in the Catalogue of the moſt famous Old-Teſtament Saints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. let any Man judg. Or whether it be reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> who durſt not ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God in complying with the luſtful Deſires of his Miſtreſs, would have ſo little Conſcience as to cheat a whole Nation into Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, let common Senſe determine. But if our Author had been ſo <hi>good</hi> as to have had more frequent Converſe with this <hi>good Book,</hi> he might have found that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was as Abſolute before <hi>Joſeph</hi> was of his Council as after; for, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.40. he told him, That according to his Word ſhould all his People be ruled. And, <hi>ver.</hi> 44. That without him No Man ſhould lift up Hand nor Foot in all the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (could never have promiſed had it not been in his Power. Neither was it the whole ſeven Years Plenty that he brought into <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Granaries, but only the fifth part of it, as appears from <hi>ver.</hi> 34. Nay, ſo far was <hi>Joſeph</hi> from enſlaving them, that though he had actually bought themſelves and all that they had for <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that he not only ſav'd their Lives, as they themſelves did acknowledg, and kept Bread in the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> when there was none elſewhere, but left them in as good a Condition after the Famine, as they were in during the Plenty, as may be ſeen from <hi>Chap.</hi> 47.26. by giving them four parts of the Land to themſelves, and taking only a. Fifth for <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as he had in the Years of Plenty; and though <hi>Joſeph</hi> brought this into an Eſtabliſh'd Law, yet it's more than our Author can prove, that it was not a Cuſtom before, ſeeing he directed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to lay up the fifth Part, <hi>Chap.</hi> 41.34. And that we hear of no Oppoſition made thereunto, nor unto any thing elſe that <hi>Joſeph</hi> did in the Government; but on the contrary, the People did thankfully acknowledg him as the Author of their Preſervation, and willingly obeyed him, even when he tranſplanted them from one City to another: Which it's probable they would never have conſented to, had they look'd upon it as a bringing of them into Slavery: for our Author may remember, that though a great many of his Party ſurrendred their Charters in the late Reigns, and became voluntary Slaves, yet the Nation in general could never be brought to it. And as for <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s planting his own Country-men in the beſt of the Land, it was by <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Command, and becauſe it beſt ſuited their way of living, and was a Place where they were likely to be leaſt offenſive to the Egyptians, as appears from <hi>Chap.</hi> 46.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55812:18"/>
               <hi>ver.</hi> 34. becauſe every Shepherd, and ſuch were the Iſraelites, were an Abomination to the Egyptians. And in the laſt place we have reaſon to conclude, that all this was done by the ſpecial Direction of that God who ſent him into <hi>Egypt</hi> to preſerve his People, <hi>Chap.</hi> 45. <hi>v.</hi> 7. and not according to our Author, to cheat the Egyptians into Slavery.</p>
            <p>And thus having diſcovered how falſly and impiouſly our Author hath wreſted this Hiſtory of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> I ſhall now conſider his Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than which nothing can be more Treaſonable and Malicious; for having aſcrib'd all the Miſchiefs which came upon the Egyptians to their entertaining of one Foreigner as a Privy Counſellor, What, ſays he, may that Nation expect where the Head and many of the Council are Foreigners? which is directly aim'd at His Majeſty, the Earl of <hi>Portland</hi> and others, whom God has, to the Confuſion of our Author and his Faction, made uſe of to deliver us from their Egyptian Thraldom. But our Author, that he may diſcover all his Deſign at once, does in the former part of his Speech endeavour to ſtir up the Country againſt the Parliament, and now he attempts the like againſt His Majeſty; but is he ſo fooliſh as to think that his Parallel holds as to <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Management in <hi>Egypt?</hi> Is all our Corn brought into His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Granaries? Is there not Plenty enough in the Kingdom, though ſome narrow-ſoul'd Men, like our Author, keep it at an Exceſſive rate in and about <hi>London?</hi> Has His Majeſty either made a purchaſe of our Lands, our Cattle, or our Perſons, any otherwiſe than by a Conqueſt of our Hearts? What Colony of Dutch has he planted in the beſt of our Land? or how can he be reckon'd a Foreigner who abſtracted from his being King by God and the Peoples Choice, is Son to an Engliſh Princeſs, Husband to an Engliſh Queen, governs by Engliſh Laws, and fights with Engliſh Armies for the Preſervation of our Engliſh Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? But if our Author will needs be making Compariſons, we hope that he will allow us the ſame Liberty, and then we ſhall agree that he reſembles <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in being ſent hither by God for his Peoples De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, and keeping <hi>England</hi> in Peace, while all our Neighbours are or have been involv'd in Blood. But if thoſe other Practices of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s be culpable in buying the Lands, Cattel and Perſons of the Egyptians for <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Uſe, we know of a Copy which outdoes the Original, and that is the God of his Faction <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV, who hath not bought, but plundered from his Subjects and Neighbours, all that could render their Lives comfortable. But further, we have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear any Incouragement to the Invaſion of our Liberties, or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55812:19"/>being made Slaves by the Concurrence of the Naturaliz'd Dutch. They who have been accuſtomed to live in Liberty and Freedom at Home, which they purchas'd with the beſt of their Treaſure and Blood, are not like to be fond of concurring with ſuch Meaſures as may render them Slaves Abroad: But though there is leſs hazard in this Point from the Dutch than the French, yet all along our Author is ſeverer upon the former than the latter, and makes a terrible Outcry againſt the ſending of Corn to <hi>Holland,</hi> but ſpeaks not one word of the great Stores which his Brethren the J—ites tranſport by ſtealth into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now for our Author's Concluſion. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I perceive ſome Gentlemen are uneaſy, perhaps I have offended them in ſuppoſing they are Religious Repreſentatives, or concluding that their Religion is to be prov'd from the Bible: If that be it which diſpleaſeth, I beg their Pardon, and promiſe not to offend again on that ſcore, and will conclude all with this Motion, that the Serjeant be commanded to open the Doors, and let us firſt kick the Bill out of the Houſe, and then the Foreigners out of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In truth theſe Gentlemen might well be uneaſy to hear a Fool tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in his Folly; but why they ſhould be offended to be told that their Religion was to be prov'd from the bible, whence our Author can never prove his own, is not ſo eaſy to be imagin'd, though they had reaſon enough, indeed, to be diſpleas'd to ſee an Aſs ſtrutting in a Lion's Skin; and yet I cannot tell how they could refrain from Laughter to hear the dull Creature diſcovered by its braying. And thus ſeeing our Author began with one Fable, I hope that I may be allow'd to end with another; and ſhall only add, that let him <hi>Caw,</hi> and <hi>Bray,</hi> and <hi>Kiek,</hi> and do what he pleaſes, it ſignifies nothing, ſo long as he <hi>kicks againſt the Pricks,</hi> whereof I hope that by this time he himſelf may be perſwaded; eſpecially if he conſider the diſgraceful Exit which the Commons have given to his Speech, and he may thank his Stars for having eſcap'd ſo well.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
